Guide to the Carl F. Brand Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Carl F. Brand papers
1909-1973
SC0248
Brand, Carl F., 1893-1981.
20 Linear feet
Collection contains correspondence and book reviews, Brand's manuscript of "England in the mid-nineteenth century", class notes, notes from his student days, material pertaining to classes taught by Brand at Stanford, notebooks on travel, materials on conferences and meetings, notes and pages from Brand's work, "The British Labor Party", personal and official correspondence, galleys of books, papers by Brand's students, newspaper clippings and research notes. The personal correspondence portrays life in the United States during the war years (1940's). There is also family correspondence about life in China after Japan's invasion in the 1930's.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Lois and Donald Brand, 1981.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of British history at Stanford University, 1924-1958, Brand began the Hoover Institution's British Labor Party collections. He received his A.B. from Indiana University in 1915 and A.M. in 1916; his A.M., 1918 and Ph.D. 1923 from Harvard University.
Description of the Collection
Collection contains correspondence and book reviews, Brand's manuscript of "England in the mid-nineteenth century", class notes, notes from his student days, material pertaining to classes taught by Brand at Stanford, notebooks on travel, materials on conferences and meetings, notes and pages from Brand's work, "The British Labor Party", personal and official correspondence, galleys of books, papers by Brand's students, newspaper clippings and research notes. The personal correspondence portrays life in the United States during the war years (1940's). There is also family correspondence about life in China after Japan's invasion in the 1930's.
Access Terms
Brand, Carl F., 1893-1981.; Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace --Archives.; Stanford University. Department of History. Students.; Authors.; China--History --1937-1945.; College teachers.; Great Britain--Economic conditions.; Lecture notes.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Notebooks.; Reviews.; United States--History--1933-1945.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - History and Classes, Book Reviews (Box 1)
  - Manuscript (Box 2)
  - Notes on History 106, 160, and 156 (Box 3)
  - Class notes and History Class Syllabi (Box 4)
  - History 105 and 108 (Box 5)
  - Notes from classes (Box 6)
  - History courses, syllabi and notes (Box 7)
  - History courses, syllabi and notes (Box 8)
  - Notebooks on travel (Box 9)
  - Notes on books (Box 10)
  - Notes on books (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 12)
  - Galleys from books (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous: correspondence and articles (Box 14)
  - Official Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Chapters: "The British Labour Party" and "The General Election of 1970 – Britain" (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1973 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1949 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1947 (Box 19)
  - History notes, history class notes, papers on history (Box 20)
  - Student reports (Box 21)
  - Note cards: English history 1838-54, 1860-69; Labour Party and Nationalization (Box 22)
  - Note cards: "1914-1923"; General Election 1955, 1959; Labour Party and Wartine Coalitions (Box 23)
  - Note cards: Wilson & Europe; "1966-68"; English history 1833-37 (Box 24)
  - Note cards: "III 1925-29"; English Foreign Policy; "1970" (Box 25)
  - Note cards: Peace Project; LP and CP (Box 26)
  - Note cards: First Wilson government; "1969-" (Box 27)
  - Note cards: Eastern Europe (Box 28)
  - Note cards: [no subject listed] (Box 29)